<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short catechisme contayning the princples [sic] of religion : verie profitable for all sorts of people.</title>
            <author>Ball, John, 1585-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1313.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23228641</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23228641</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26409</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02987)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26409)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1807:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short catechisme contayning the princples [sic] of religion : verie profitable for all sorts of people.</title>
                  <author>Ball, John, 1585-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The thirteenth impression.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby and are to be sold by Ed. Brewster and Rob. Bird, in Pauls Church-yard and in Cheape-side at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Ball by STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸(-A1) B-C⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Magdalene College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26409:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26409:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT Catechiſme. Contayning the Princples of RELIGION. <hi>Verie profitable for all ſorts of</hi> PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The thirteenth Impreſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Ed. Brewſter</hi> and <hi>Rob. Bird,</hi> in Pauls Church-yard and in Cheape-ſide at the Signe of the Bible. 1630.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:26409:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26409:2"/>
            <head>A Short Catechiſme.</head>
            <p>Q. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat ought to be the Chiefe and continuall care of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man in this life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To glorifie <hi rend="sup">a</hi> God, and ſaue his <hi rend="sup">b</hi> ſoule. <hi>a</hi> 1. Cor. 10.31. <hi>b</hi> Act. 16.30.31. Matth. 16.26.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whence muſt wee take direction to attaine hereunto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Out of the word of God <hi rend="sup">c</hi> alone. <hi>c</hi> Iohn 20.31.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What call you the word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The holy Scripture immediately <hi rend="sup">d</hi> inſpired, which is contained in the Bookes of the Old and New Teſtament. <hi>d</hi> 2. Tim. 3.16</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the Bookes of the Old Teſtament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Moſes, <hi rend="sup">e</hi> and the Prophets. <hi>e</hi> Luke 24.27.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which are the Bookes of the new Teſtament?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:26409:3"/>
            <p> A. Matthew, Marke, Luke, and the reſt, as they follow in our Bibles.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may it bee proned that thoſe Bookes are the word of God, immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the Holy Ghost to the Prophets and Apoſtles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By the teſtimonie of the <hi rend="sup">f</hi> Church, conſtancie <hi rend="sup">g</hi> of the Saints, miracles wrought to confirme the truth, and the Antiquitie <hi rend="sup">i</hi> thereof. <hi>f</hi> 2. Pet. 1.19. <hi>g</hi> Reu. 6.9. <hi>h</hi> 1. King. 17.24. Iohn 3.2. <hi>i</hi> Ier. 6.16. Heb. 13.8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By the <hi rend="sup">k</hi> ſtile, <hi rend="sup">l</hi> efficacie, ſweete <hi rend="sup">m</hi> conſent, admirable <hi rend="sup">n</hi> doctrine, excellent <hi rend="sup">o</hi> end, and the witneſſe <hi rend="sup">p</hi> of the Scripture <hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſelfe <hi>k</hi> Gen. 17.1. Pſal. 50.1. Eſa. 44.24. Gen. 2.17. Exod. 20.1.2. Ioel. 1.1.2.1. Cor 11.23. Ioh. 3.36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Cor. 1.23.24. <hi rend="sup">l</hi> Pſa. 19 8. Rom. 15.4. Act. 5.38.39. Rom. 7.7. Zach. 13.2. Zeph. 2.11. Act. 9.5.20.21. Phil. 1.12, 13. Rom. 15.19. 2. Cor. 4.8, 9.10. <hi>m</hi> Gen. 3.15. and 49.10. Eſa. 9.6. Dan. 2.24. Matth. 1.18. Act. 10.43. <hi>n</hi> Pſa. 119 129.138.172. Deut. 4.5.6. <hi>o</hi> Ioh. 20.31 <hi>p</hi> 2. Tim. 3.16. 2. Pet. 1.19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Theſe reaſons may conuince any, be he neuer ſo obſtinate; but are they ſufficient to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26409:3"/>perſwade the heart thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: the teſtimonie of the Spirit is <hi rend="sup">q</hi> neceſſary; and onely <hi rend="sup">r</hi> all-ſufficient for this purpoſe. <hi>q</hi> 1. Cor. 2.14. <hi>r.</hi> 1 Ioh. 2.20.27.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the properties of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is of Diuine <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> authoritie, the rule <hi rend="sup">t</hi> of faith and Manners, <hi rend="sup">u</hi> neceſſarie, <hi rend="sup">w</hi> pure, <hi rend="sup">x</hi> perfect, and <hi rend="sup">y</hi> plaine. <hi>ſ</hi> 2. Tim. 3.16. <hi>t</hi> Eccle. 12.10. Galat. 6.16. <hi>u</hi> Rom. 10.14. <hi>w</hi> Pſal. 12.6. <hi>x</hi> Pſal. 19.7. <hi>y.</hi> Pro. 8.9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>For what end was the Scripture written?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To teach, inſtruct, conuince, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and comfort. 2. Tim. 3.16.17. Rom. 15.4.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Doth the knowledge of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res belong vnto all men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes, all men are not only <hi rend="sup">a</hi> allowed, but exhorted, and commanded to <hi rend="sup">b</hi> read, heare, and <hi rend="sup">c</hi> vnderſtand the Scriptures. <hi>a</hi> Ioh. 5.3.39. <hi>b.</hi> Deut. 17.18.19. Reue. 1.3. <hi>c.</hi> Act. 8.30.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>The Scriptures were written in Hebrew and Greeke, how then ſhall all menread, and vnderſtand them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They ought to be <hi rend="sup">d</hi> tranſlated into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26409:4"/>knowne tongues, and <hi rend="sup">e</hi> interperted. <hi>d</hi> 1. Cor. 14.18.19. <hi>e</hi> Neh. 8.8. Act. 8.35.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Scripture eſpecially teach vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The ſauing <hi rend="sup">f</hi> knowledge of God, and Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>f</hi> Iohn 17.3. Col. 2.1.2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may it bee prooued that there is a God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By the <hi rend="sup">g</hi> workes, and <hi rend="sup">h</hi> wonders which are ſeene, the teſtimonie of <hi rend="sup">i</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the powers <hi rend="sup">k</hi> of the ſoule, and the practiſes <hi rend="sup">l</hi> of Satan. <hi>g</hi> Pſal. 19.1.2. Eſa. 41.23. Rom. 120. Act. 14.17. Iob. 12.7.8.9. <hi>h</hi> Exod. 8.19. and 9.16. <hi>i</hi> Rom. 2.15. Eſa. 33.14. Pſal. 14.5. and 53.5. <hi>k</hi> Zach. 12.1. Pſal. 94.8.9.10. <hi>l</hi> Reuel. 12.7.10.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>How elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By the conſent of Nations, defence of the <hi rend="sup">m</hi> Church, <hi rend="sup">n</hi> ſupport, and comfort of the godly, but principally by <hi rend="sup">o</hi> the Scriptures, <hi>m</hi> Pſal 9.16. and 58.10.11. <hi>n</hi> Iere. 33.9. <hi>o</hi> Eſa. 42.8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He is a <hi rend="sup">p</hi> Spirit, hauing his being of <hi rend="sup">q</hi> himſelfe. <hi>p</hi> Ioh. 4.24. <hi>q</hi> Exod. 3.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Gods be there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Onely one <hi rend="sup">r</hi> God, and three <hi rend="sup">r</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26409:4"/>
               <hi>r</hi> Deut. 6.4. 1. Cor. 8.4.6. <hi>ſ</hi> Matth. 28.19. 1. Iohn 5.7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the propertie of the Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To bee of himſelfe, and to <hi rend="sup">t</hi> beget his Sonne. <hi>t</hi> Iohn 1.18. and 3.16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the propertie of the Sonne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To bee begotten <hi rend="sup">u</hi> of the Father. <hi>u</hi> Iohn 3.18.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the propertie of the Holy Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To proceed from the <hi>w</hi> Father, and the <hi rend="sup">x</hi> Sonne. <hi>w</hi> Iohn 15.26. <hi>x</hi> Rom. 8.9. Gal. 4.6.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>The nature of God is infinite and incomprehenſible, how then may we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By his <hi rend="sup">y</hi> properties, and by his <hi rend="sup">z</hi> workes. <hi>y</hi> Exod. 34.6.7. <hi>z</hi> Pſalm. 19.1. and 8.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are his properties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He is moſt <hi rend="sup">a</hi> wiſe, <hi rend="sup">b</hi> ſtrong, <hi rend="sup">c</hi> good, <hi rend="sup">d</hi> gracious, <hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt, <hi rend="sup">f</hi> mercifull, <hi rend="sup">g</hi> perfect, <hi rend="sup">h</hi> bleſſed, and <hi rend="sup">i</hi> glorius. <hi>a</hi> Rom. 16.27. <hi>b</hi> Iob. 12.13. <hi>c</hi> Matth. 19.17. <hi>d</hi> Exod. 33.19. Rom. 5.8. <hi>e</hi> Pſal. 145.17. <hi>f</hi> Pſal. 103.11. and 145.8.9. <hi>g</hi> Mat. 5.48. Iob. 35.7.8. <hi>h</hi> Mar. 14.61. Rom. 9.5. <hi>i</hi> 1. Cor. 2.8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are his workes?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:26409:5"/>
            <p> A. They are three, Decree, Creation, and Prouidence.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Decree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That whereby God hath from eternitie ſet <hi rend="sup">k</hi> downe with himſelfe whatſoeuer ſhall come to paſſe. <hi>k</hi> Epheſ. 1.11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That wherby God made all things of <hi rend="sup">l</hi> nothing, in ſix <hi rend="sup">m</hi> dayes. <hi>l</hi> Heb. 11.3. <hi>m</hi> Exod. 20.11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what forme or manner were all things created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A In an execellent order, <hi rend="sup">n</hi> and excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi rend="sup">o</hi> good. <hi>n.</hi> Iere. 10.12. <hi>o</hi> Gene. 1.31.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>For what end did God make all things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. For the praiſe of his power, <hi rend="sup">p</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wiſdome, perfection, and freedome. <hi>p</hi> Prou. 16.4. Reue. 4.11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is prouidence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That whereby God doth <hi rend="sup">q</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and gouerne <hi rend="sup">r</hi> all things with all their actions. <hi>q</hi> Pſal. 36.6. 1. Tim. 4.10. <hi>r</hi> Prou. 15.3. Matth. 10.29.30.31.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What are the ſpeciall creatures made, preſerued, and gouerned by the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Angels, <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> and men. <hi>ſ</hi> Heb. 2.7. Col. 1.16.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:26409:5"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>What was the ſtate of aman by creation</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Marueilous, <hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy, and happy <hi>t</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eleſ. 7.29. or 31.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why ſay you that man was holy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Becauſe he was <hi rend="sup">u</hi> created after the image of God, in knowledge, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and true holineſſe. <hi>u</hi> Gen. 1.26. Col. 3.10. Epeſ. 4.23.24.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein did mans happines conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. In the inioying <hi rend="sup">w</hi> of ſweete peace and communion with God. <hi>w</hi> Gen. 1.29.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What further priuiledges did Man enioy in this ſtate of innocencie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He was placed in <hi rend="sup">x</hi> Paradiſe, had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to eate of euery tree <hi rend="sup">y</hi> of the garden, except the <hi rend="sup">z</hi> tree of knowlede of good and euill, and was made <hi rend="sup">a</hi> ruler of alearth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Creatures. <hi>x</hi> Gen. 2.15. <hi>y</hi> Gen. 2.16. <hi>z.</hi> Gen. 2.17. <hi>a</hi> Gen. 2.19 Pſal. 8.6.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were theſe things beſtowed vpon man that he might liue as he liſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: but that he might ſerue <hi rend="sup">b</hi> the Lord his maker who therefore gaue man a <hi rend="sup">c</hi> law, binding him alwayes to perfect obedience, and a ſpecial commandement to trie him. <hi>b</hi> Reuel. 4.11. Pſal. 95.6. <hi>c</hi> Rom. 2.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What was that ſpeciall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:26409:6"/>
            <p> A. Of the tree of knowledge of good and <hi rend="sup">d</hi> euill, thou ſhalt not eate: for in the day that thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt die the death. <hi>d</hi> Gene. 2.17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Death wee heare was threatned if he diſobeyed, what promiſe was made to encolourage him to his dutie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The <hi rend="sup">e</hi> continuance both of himſelfe, and his poſteritie in that good eſtate. <hi>e</hi> Gen. 2.9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did man continue in that good eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: but he fell from <hi rend="sup">f</hi> God, through the inticement of Satan. <hi>f</hi> 1. Tim. 2.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How did he fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By ſinning wilfully <hi rend="sup">g</hi> againſt God, <hi rend="sup">h</hi> tranſgreſſing his Law: <hi>g</hi> Eccleſ. 7.29. or 31. Rom. 5.12. <hi>h</hi> 1. Ioh. 3.4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What was the ſinne he did commit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The eating of <hi rend="sup">i</hi> the forbidden fruit. <hi>i</hi> Gen. 3.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Did all mankind ſinne in Adam?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes <hi rend="sup">k</hi> for wee were all in his loynes. <hi>k</hi> Rom. 5.12. 1 Cor. 15.22. Heb. 7.9.10.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſtate of all men by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Adams fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They are dead in <hi rend="sup">l</hi> ſin, and bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaues of Satan. <hi>l</hi> Eph. 2.1.2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth that appeare?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:26409:6"/>
            <p> A. In that they are altogether <hi rend="sup">m</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to good, and <hi rend="sup">n</hi> prone to euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually. <hi>m</hi> 2. Cor. 3.5. <hi>n</hi> Gen. 8.21.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What fruits doe proceed from this originall corruption?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Euill <hi rend="sup">o</hi> thoughts, words, <hi rend="sup">p</hi> &amp; works. <hi>o</hi> Gen. 6.5. <hi>p</hi> Gal. 5.19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are all the actions of naturall men euill continually?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes, for they <hi rend="sup">q</hi> faile in many things, and therefore as they come from them, they are odious <hi rend="sup">r</hi> vnto God. <hi>q</hi> Matth. 12.35. <hi>r</hi> Prou. 28.9.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What puniſhments are due vnto man, by reaſon of thoſe ſinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All woe, <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> and miſerie, temporall, ſpiritual, and eternall, <hi>ſ</hi> Lam. 3.39. Rom. 6.23. Gal. 3.10.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the temporall miſeries?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Gods curſe vpon the <hi rend="sup">t</hi> creatures, on <hi rend="sup">u</hi> mans body, ſenſes, name, friends, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hee takes in hand; and death <hi rend="sup">u</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>t</hi> Rom. 8.20. <hi>u</hi> Deut. 28.15.16. &amp;c. <hi>u</hi> Rom. 6.21.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which are the ſpirituall miſeries?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Blindnes of <hi rend="sup">x</hi> minde, the ſpirt of <hi rend="sup">y</hi> ſlumber, and giddineſſe, horror of <hi rend="sup">z</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, hardneſſe of <hi rend="sup">a</hi> heart, a reprobate,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26409:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:26409:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:26409:8"/>ſenſe, and ſtrong <hi rend="sup">c</hi> deluſions. <hi>x</hi> Eſa. 6.9. <hi>y</hi> Rom. 11.8. <hi>z.</hi> Matt. 27.3.4.5. <hi>a</hi> Exod. 7.3. <hi>b</hi> Rom. 1.28. <hi>c</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the eternall miſerie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Euerlaſting <hi rend="sup">d</hi> damnation. <hi>d.</hi> Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 6.23</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>After a man doth know his miſerie, what is he to learne in the next place?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The true meanes how he may eſcape the foreſaid <hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſerie, and be reſtored to <hi rend="sup">f</hi> happineſſe. <hi>e</hi> Act 2.37. <hi>f</hi> Act. 16.30.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>By what meanes may we eſcape this miſerie, and recouer happineſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Only by Ieſus <hi rend="sup">g</hi> Chriſt. <hi>g.</hi> Act. 4.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The eternall Son <hi rend="sup">h</hi> of God, who in time became man for his elect. <hi>h</hi> Gal. 4.4.5</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many things are we to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. His <hi rend="sup">i</hi> Perſon and his <hi rend="sup">k</hi> Office <hi>i</hi> Col. 2.9. <hi>k</hi> Heb. 2.16.17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is his Perſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is God <hi rend="sup">l</hi> and man, vnited toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into one <hi rend="sup">m</hi> perſon <hi>l</hi> Ioh. 1.14. Rom. 9.5. Eſa. 7.14. <hi>m</hi> 1. Cor 8.6.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Being God before all time how could he be made man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Hee was conceiued by the <hi rend="sup">n</hi> holy Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Marie, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26409:8"/>to the <hi rend="sup">o</hi> Prophets <hi>n</hi> Luke 1.35. <hi>o</hi> Gene. 3.15. Eſa. 7.14. and 11.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was Chriſt Conceiued by the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That hee might be pure <hi rend="sup">p</hi> without ſinne, wherewith all are ſtained, that are conceiued after the ordinarie <hi rend="sup">q</hi> manner. <hi>p</hi> Luke 1.45. <hi>q</hi> Ioh. 3.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why was he God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That hee might beare the weight of Gods wrath without ſinking vnder it, ouercome death, bee the Head of the Church repaire his Image in vs, conquer the enemies of our ſaluation, and defend vs againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why was he man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That he might ſuffer death <hi rend="sup">r</hi> for vs, ſanctifie our <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> nature, and we might haue acceſſe with <hi rend="sup">t</hi> boldueſſe to the throne of grace <hi>r</hi> Heb. 2.14. <hi>ſ</hi> Heb. 2.11. <hi>t</hi> Heb. 4.15.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is his Office?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A To bee a Mediator, <hi rend="sup">u</hi> to reconcile God and man <hi>u</hi> 1. Tim. 2.5.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How did he that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By his fulfilling <hi>w</hi> the law, and by his <hi rend="sup">x</hi> ſufferings. Matth. 3.15. <hi>x</hi> Heb. 9.15. Rom. 5.10.12.13.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26409:9"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>What vnderſtand you by his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. His voluntarie <hi rend="sup">y</hi> humiliation both in <hi rend="sup">z</hi> ſoule and bodie, his <hi rend="sup">a</hi> crucifying death, <hi rend="sup">b</hi> buriall, and abiding <hi rend="sup">c</hi> vnder the dominion of death, for a time. <hi>y</hi> Phil. 2.5.6.7.8. <hi>z</hi> Eſa. 53.10. Matth. 26.38. Heb. 9.14. <hi>a</hi> Luke 23.33. <hi>b</hi> 1. Cor. 15.3.4. <hi>c.</hi> Acts. 2.27.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did Chriſt alwayes abide vnder the power and dominion of death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: for the power of death being <hi rend="sup">d</hi> ſubdued, the third <hi rend="sup">e</hi> day he roſe againe aſcended <hi rend="sup">f</hi> into heauen, and ſitteth at the right hand of the Father. <hi>d</hi> Acts 2.31. <hi>e</hi> 1. Cor. 15.3.4. <hi>f</hi> Marke 16.19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the ſpeciall parts of Chriſt Mediatorſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Hee is <hi rend="sup">g</hi> Prophet, <hi rend="sup">h</hi> Prieſt, and <hi rend="sup">i</hi> King. <hi>g</hi> Act. 3.22. <hi>h</hi> Heb. 2.17. <hi>i</hi> Pſ. 110.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was Chriſt a Prophet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Toreueale vnto vs the way to <hi rend="sup">k</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life. <hi>k</hi> Luk. 4.18.19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was he a Prieſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To purchaſe for vs <hi rend="sup">l</hi> righteouſneſſe and life eternall. <hi>l</hi> Heb. 5.9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the functions of his Prieſtly office?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:26409:9"/>
            <p> A. <hi rend="sup">m</hi> Offering vp himſelfe a ſacrifice once for all, and making requeſt for vs. <hi>m</hi> Heb. 5.1. and 9.26. and 7.25.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was Christ a King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To bridle, and <hi rend="sup">n</hi> ſubdue all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; but to <hi rend="sup">o</hi> gather and <hi rend="sup">p</hi> gouerne his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and choſen. <hi>n</hi> Col. 2.14. Pſal. 110.1, 2. 1. Corinth. 15.28. <hi>o</hi> Iohn 19.16. Hag. 2.7. <hi>p</hi> Ezech. 34.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What benefit doe we receiue by the death and reſurrection of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Wee are redeemed from the <hi rend="sup">q</hi> guilt puniſhment, and power of <hi rend="sup">r</hi> ſin, and ſhall bee raiſed <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> vp at the laſt day, <hi>q</hi> Gal. 3.13. Coloſ. 1.14. <hi>r</hi> Luke 1.74. Titus 2.14. <hi>ſ</hi> 1. Cor. 15.13.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How are wee redeemed from the guilt and puniſhment of ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. God the Father, accepting the death of Chriſt, as a ful ranſome <hi rend="sup">t</hi> &amp; ſatisfaction to his iuſtice, doth freely diſcharge and acquit vs from all our ſins. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Rom. 3.24.25. Col. 1.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How are wee redeemed from the power and tyrannie of ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Chriſt by his death killeth <hi rend="sup">a</hi> ſinne in vs, and by his reſurrection doth quicken vs to newneſſe of life. <hi>a</hi> Rom. 6.3.4.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:26409:10"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>What are the benefits of Chriſts aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; ſitting at the right hand of the Father</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A The leading <hi rend="sup">u</hi> of captiuitie captiue, the giuing of gifts vnto men, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi rend="sup">x</hi> of his ſpirit vpon his people, and the preparing <hi rend="sup">y</hi> a place for them, <hi>u</hi> Eph. 4.11. <hi>x</hi> Acts 2.16, 17. <hi>y</hi> Iohn 14.3.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the benefits of his interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The perſons of the faithfull doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies remaine iuſt, and their works <hi rend="sup">z</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in the ſight of God; hereby alſo they are defended againſt the accuſations of all their enemies, <hi>z</hi> 1. Pet. 2.5. Gen. 4.4 Exod. 28.38.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How will the knowledge of theſe things worke in the heart of him whom God will ſaue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It brings him to a ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi rend="sup">a</hi> of his owne eſtate, to grieue <hi rend="sup">b</hi> for ſinne, and the feare of Gods diſpleaſure, whereby the <hi rend="sup">c</hi> heart is broken and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, <hi>a</hi> Ier. 8.6.7. Luk. 15.17. <hi>b</hi> Acts 2.37. <hi>c</hi> Acts 9.6.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What elſe will this knowledge worke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I <hi rend="sup">c</hi> will bring a man to confeſſe <hi rend="sup">d</hi> his ſinne, highly to <hi rend="sup">e</hi> prize Chriſt, and hunger <hi rend="sup">f</hi> after him, vntill hee obtaine his deſire.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26409:10"/>
               <hi>d</hi> Luke 15.18. <hi>e</hi> Math. 13.44. <hi>f</hi> Eſa. 55.1. Iohn 7.37.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How are we made partakers of Chriſt with all his benefits?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A By faith <hi rend="sup">g</hi> alone <hi>g</hi> Iohn 3.16. and 1.12. Acts 13.39.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A reſting vpon Chriſt <hi rend="sup">h</hi> alone for ſaluation. <hi>h</hi> Pſal. 2.12. Acts 16.31.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the ground of faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The free promiſes <hi rend="sup">i</hi> of God made in Chriſt, concerning the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and eternall righteouſnes. <hi>i</hi> Rom. 4.18. Heb. 11, 11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is faith wrought in vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Inwardly by the ſpirit, as the <hi rend="sup">k</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, &amp; outwardly by the <hi rend="sup">l</hi> preaching of the word and <hi rend="sup">m</hi> catechiſing, as the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof. <hi>k</hi> Act. 16.14. <hi>l</hi> Rom. 10.14 <hi>m</hi> Heb. 5.11.12. and 6.2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth the Word worke faith in vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By ſhewing vs our <hi rend="sup">n</hi> miſery, and the true meanes of our <hi rend="sup">o</hi> recouery, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi rend="sup">p</hi> vs being humbled, to receiue the promiſes of the Goſpel. <hi>n</hi> Rom. 7.7. Gal. 3 22. <hi>o</hi> Gal. 4.4, 5. <hi>p</hi> Matth. 11.28. Eſay 61.1, 2.3. Reuel. 22.17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth the ſpirit work by the Word?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:26409:11"/>
            <p> A. It doth teach vs wiſedome, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <hi rend="sup">q</hi> things generally ſpoken, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our ſelues, ſecretly vpholdeth <hi rend="sup">r</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deſpair, ſtirreth vp in vs good <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, doth ſoften <hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heart, <hi rend="sup">u</hi> &amp; draw vs to reſt vpon Chriſt for ſaluation, before we haue <hi rend="sup">w</hi> the feeling of comfort. <hi>q</hi> Ezek. 36.27.31. <hi>r</hi> Pſal. 51.12. <hi>ſ</hi> Phil. 2.13. <hi>t</hi> Ezech. 11.19. and 36.26. <hi>u</hi> Iohn 6.44. <hi>w</hi> Matth. 11.28.29.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>By what meanes is faith increaſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By hearing the ſame <hi rend="sup">x</hi> word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and catechiſed, and likewiſe by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi rend="sup">y</hi> prayer. <hi>x</hi> 1. Pet. 2.2. <hi>y</hi> Luke 17.5</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How must wee heare that wee may get profit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. With <hi rend="sup">z</hi> reuerence, <hi rend="sup">a</hi> meeknes, <hi rend="sup">b</hi> ioy, a <hi rend="sup">c</hi> longing deſire to learne, and giuing <hi rend="sup">d</hi> credit to the truth. <hi>z</hi> Eſa. 66.2.5. <hi>a</hi> I am. 1 21. <hi>b</hi> Mat. 13.44. <hi>c</hi> 1. Pet. 2.2. <hi>d</hi> Heb. 4.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Wee muſt meditate <hi rend="sup">c</hi> of that wee heare, apply it to our ſelues, conferre <hi rend="sup">f</hi> of it with others, and with <hi rend="sup">g</hi> diligence ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the practice of what is required. <hi>c</hi> Pſal. 1.2. and 119.14.15. <hi>f</hi> Ioh. 4.53. <hi>g</hi> Eſay 2.3. Luke 2.15.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:26409:11"/>
            <p> A. It is a calling vpon God, in the name of Chriſt, with the <hi rend="sup">h</hi> heart, and ſometimes with the voice, according to his will: for our ſelues and <hi rend="sup">i</hi> others. <hi>h</hi> Exod. 14.15. 1. Sam. 1.13. <hi>i</hi> 1. Iohn 5.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>To whom must we pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To God alone, in the name <hi rend="sup">k</hi> of Chriſt. <hi>k</hi> Iohn 16.23.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Ought we not in prayer to make parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular confeſſion of our ſinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes: ſo farre as we can <hi rend="sup">l</hi> come to the knowledge of them; and this we muſt do with <hi rend="sup">m</hi> griefe, hatred and ſhame, freely <hi rend="sup">n</hi> accuſing and condemning our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, with broken <hi rend="sup">o</hi> and contrite hearts. <hi>l</hi> 1. Sam. 12.19. Pſal. 19.12. <hi>m</hi> Neh. 8.9. <hi>n</hi> Neh. 9.33. <hi>o</hi> Zach. 12.10.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Petition and Thankſgiuing.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is a Prayer, wherein wee deſire the <hi rend="sup">p</hi> preuenting or <hi rend="sup">q</hi> remouing of things hurtfull, &amp; the obtaining of things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full either for this life, or for that which is to come. <hi>p</hi> Eſa. 37.20. Mat. 6.13. <hi>q</hi> Pſal. 6.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How must wee make our requests that we may be heard?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:26409:12"/>
            <p> A. With <hi rend="sup">r</hi> vnderſtanding feeling of <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> our wants, <hi rend="sup">t</hi> feruency, <hi rend="sup">u</hi> reuerence, hope <hi rend="sup">w</hi> to ſpeed, &amp; <hi rend="sup">x</hi> loue, <hi>r</hi> 1. Cor. 14.15. <hi>ſ</hi> Mat. 11.28. <hi>t</hi> Iam. 5.16.17. <hi>u</hi> Eccleſ. 5.2. <hi>w</hi> 1. Tim. 2.8. <hi>x</hi> Mat. 6.14. Mar. 11.25.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What is thankeſgiuing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is <hi rend="sup">y</hi> prayer, wherein wee render thankes to God, for his <hi rend="sup">z</hi> generall good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and particular <hi rend="sup">a</hi> fauors. <hi>y</hi> 1. Sam. 2.1. <hi>z</hi> Pſal. 136.1. &amp;c. <hi>a</hi> Pſal. 103.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What things are required in thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Loue to <hi rend="sup">b</hi> God, and ioy in <hi rend="sup">c</hi> his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, a deſire to <hi rend="sup">d</hi> draw others to obey and glorifie God, and an endeauour <hi rend="sup">e</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in godlineſſe our ſelues. <hi>b</hi> Pſal. 18.1.2. <hi>c</hi> Pſal. 126.1 2. <hi>d</hi> Pſalm. 34.11. <hi>e</hi> Deut. 6.10, 11.12, 13.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What rule of direction is there accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which we ought to frame our prayers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The generall direction is the word of God, the more ſpeciall is the Lords Prayer.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many things are to bee conſidered in the Lords Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Three, the Preface, the Prayer it felfe, and the Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the Preface?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:26409:12"/>
            <p> A. Our Father which art in heauen.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What learne you out of this Preface?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That God is our Father by grace and adoption, through Ieſus Chriſt, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in Maieſtie and infinite in power, that both can, and hath promiſed to helpe vs.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What are you to conſider in the Prayer itſelfe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Sixe petitions and a thankſgiuing.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the first petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Hallowed be thy name.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What deſire you of God in this petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That Gods infinite excellencie may bee magnified by vs on earth, in heart, word, and deede.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thy kingdome come.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doe you deſire of God in this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That Chriſt would conuert ſuch as be vnder the power of Satan; rule in the hearts of his choſen by his Spirit here, and perfect their ſaluation in heauen hereafter.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thy will bee done in earth, as it is in heauen.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:26409:13"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>What deſire you of God in this petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That whatſoeuer God willeth in his word might be obeyed chearefully, ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, faithfully, &amp; conſtantly by men on earth, as the Angels doe in heauen.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Giue vs this day our daily bread.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What deſire you of God in this petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That God would beſtow on vs all things neceſſarie for this life; as foode, maintenance, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fift petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What deſire you of God in this petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That God of his free mercy in Ieſus Chriſt, would fully pardon all our ſinnes, as we doe pardon the wrongs and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries we receiue from others.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſixt petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. And lead vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What deſire you of God in this petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To bee freed from trials ſo farre as it may ſtand with the good pleaſure of God, and alwayes to bee deliuered from the euill thereof, that we faint not vnder them, or be foiled by them.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:26409:13"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>Which is the thanks-giuing in the Lords prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. For thine is the kingdom, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the glory, for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doe not theſe words containe a reaſon alſo, why wee beg the former bleſſings at the hand of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes: for ſeeing the kingdome, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and glory is the Lords, we ſhould call vpon him in all our neceſſities.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the concluſion of the Lords prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Amen,</hi> which is a witneſſing of our faith, and deſire of the things prayed for.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What doth</hi> Amen <hi>ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. So it is, or, So be it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt we doe after we haue prayed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Obſerue how wee ſpeed, and what anſwer we freceiue. <hi>f</hi> Pſal. 3.4. and 85.8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What benefit ſhall we gaine hereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It wil ſtirre vp the heart to <hi rend="sup">g</hi> thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, remoue dulneſſe <hi rend="sup">h</hi> &amp; negligence in this dutie, ſtrengthen our <hi rend="sup">i</hi> faith, and in flame our hearts with zeale, ioy, &amp; loue <hi>g</hi> Pſal. 31.21, 22. <hi>h</hi> Pſal. 88.13. &amp; 4.1, 2. <hi>i</hi> Pſal. 4.3. <hi>k</hi> Pſal. 116.1. Pſal. 28.6, 7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt we doe if God anſwer vs not at the firſt or ſecond time?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:26409:14"/>
            <p> A. Examine how <hi rend="sup">l</hi> we pray, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue <hi rend="sup">m</hi> feruent therin, waiting vpon <hi rend="sup">n</hi> the Lord vntill we ſpeed. <hi>l</hi> Iam. 4.3. <hi>m</hi> Luke 18.1. <hi>n</hi> Hab. 2.3. Pſal. 5.3</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who ought to pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Though God require it of all men vpon earth, yet it more ſpecially belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the members <hi rend="sup">o</hi> of the Church mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, <hi>o</hi> Matth. 7.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who can, and may pray with hope to ſpeede?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Onely they that depart <hi rend="sup">p</hi> from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, <hi>p</hi> Pſal. 66.18.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>For whom muſt we pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. For all ſorts of men now <hi rend="sup">q</hi> liuing or that ſhall liue <hi rend="sup">r</hi> hereafter, but not for <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> the dead. <hi>q</hi> 1. Tim. 2.1.2. <hi>r</hi> Ioh. 17.20. <hi>ſ</hi> Luke 16.24, 25.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May men content themſelues to pray in priuate onely, or onely in publike?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: but they muſt vſe both <hi rend="sup">t</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and priuate <hi rend="sup">u</hi> prayer, <hi>t</hi> Acts 2.42. <hi>u</hi> Luke 11.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What other meanes hath God appointed to increaſe faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The due adminiſtration and <hi rend="sup">w</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Sacraments. <hi>w</hi> Gen. 17.9, 10, 11. Rom. 4.11.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:26409:14"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>Who ought to adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Onely they that are <hi rend="sup">x</hi> lawfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thereunto by the Church, <hi>x</hi> Heb. 5.4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A ſeale of the <hi rend="sup">x</hi> couenant of grace. <hi>x</hi> Rom. 4.11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what words is this couenant expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I will be thy <hi rend="sup">y</hi> God, and thou ſhalt be my people, <hi>y</hi> Ier. 31.33.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Two; An outward viſible ſigne, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, to repreſent &amp; ſeale another thing to the minde, and heart; and an inward grace, which is the thing ſignified.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who is author of the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The Lord <hi rend="sup">z</hi> onely, who made the couenant, <hi>z</hi> Eſa. 7.14 and 38.7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Sacraments are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Two; <hi rend="sup">a</hi> Baptiſme, and the Lords <hi rend="sup">b</hi> Supper. <hi>a</hi> Ioh 1.26. <hi>b</hi> Luke 22.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A Sacrament of our <hi rend="sup">c</hi> ingrafting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, communion with him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Church. <hi>c</hi> Mat. 28.19. Act 8.38.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the outward ſigne?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:26409:15"/>
            <p> A. Water, <hi rend="sup">d</hi> wherwith the party bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed is waſhed, <hi rend="sup">e</hi> by dipping or ſprinkling in the name <hi rend="sup">f</hi> of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt. <hi>d</hi> Acts 10.47. <hi>e</hi> Mat. 3.6.11.13.16. Acts 16.15. <hi>f</hi> Mat. 28.19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the inward grace, or thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Forgiueneſſe <hi rend="sup">f</hi> of ſinnes, and <hi rend="sup">g</hi> ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification. <hi>f</hi> Mat. 1.4. Act. 2.38. <hi>g</hi> Tit. 3.5</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>To what condition doth the party bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed binde himſelfe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To beleeue in <hi rend="sup">h</hi> Chriſt, and forſake his ſinne. <hi>h</hi> Act. 8.37. <hi>i</hi> Mar. 3.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How oft ought a man to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is enough <hi rend="sup">k</hi> once to bee baptized; for baptiſme is a pledg <hi rend="sup">l</hi> of our new birth <hi>k</hi> Acts 7.8. <hi>l</hi> Tit. 3.5.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who ought to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Infidels <hi rend="sup">m</hi> conuerted to the faith, and the infants <hi rend="sup">n</hi> of one or both Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an parents. <hi>m</hi> Acts 8.12. <hi>n</hi> Acts 2.39. 1. Cor. 7.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A Sacrament of our <hi rend="sup">a</hi> continuance and growth in Chriſt. <hi>a</hi> 1. Cor. 10.16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who is the author of this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The <hi rend="sup">b</hi> Lord Ieſus in the ſame night that he was betrayed. <hi>b</hi> 1. Cor. 11.23, 24</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:26409:15"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>What is the outward ſigne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Bread <hi rend="sup">c</hi> and Wine, with the actions pertaining to them, as breaking, giuing, receiuing, eating, and drinking. <hi>c</hi> Mat. 26 27, 28.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the inward grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Chriſt <hi rend="sup">d</hi> with all the benefits of his death and paſſion. <hi>d</hi> 1. Cor. 11.24.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the duty of the Miniſter in the adminiſtration of this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To conſecrate <hi rend="sup">e</hi> it by declaring the inſtitution thereof, and prayer ioyned with thankeſgiuing: As alſo to breake the bread, and afterwards to deliuer the bread and wine to the people. <hi>e</hi> 1. Cor. 11 23, 24. Matth. 26.26, 27, 28. Marke 14.22 Luke 22.19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is hereby ſignified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The Action of God the Father offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſt to all, and beſtowing him <hi rend="sup">f</hi> effectually vpon the worthy receiuer. <hi>f</hi> 1. Cor. 10.16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the dutie of the receiuers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To receiue <hi rend="sup">g</hi> the bread and wine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, and to eate and drinke thereof. <hi>g</hi> Matth. 26.26, 27.1. Cor. 11.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is ſignified hereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Our <hi rend="sup">h</hi> receiuing, and feeding vpon
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26409:16"/>Chriſt by faith, <hi>h</hi> 1. Cor. 10.16.</p>
            <p>Q: <hi>Is it ſufficient to receiue this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment once?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: <hi rend="sup">l</hi> but we muſt receiue it often, <hi>l</hi> Acts. 2.42. and 20.7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>For what end and vſe ought wee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To <hi rend="sup">k</hi> confirme our faith, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt, &amp; all ſauing graces in vs, to keepe <hi rend="sup">l</hi> in remembrance the Lords death vntill he come againe, and to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi rend="sup">m</hi> our loue one to another, <hi>k</hi> 1. Cor. 10.16. <hi>l</hi> 1. Cor. 11.24.26. <hi>m</hi> 1. Cor. 12.13.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the danger of vnworthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Vnworthy <hi rend="sup">n</hi> receiuers are guiltie of the body and bloud of the Lord, and doe eate and drink iudgement to themſelues. <hi>n</hi> 1. Cor. 11.27.29.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who are to receiue this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Such as know their <hi rend="sup">n</hi> miſery by ſin, the remedy thereof in Chriſt, and <hi rend="sup">o</hi> the doctrine of the Sacrament, with all ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly <hi rend="sup">p</hi> longing to bee ſatisfied with the bread of life, <hi>n</hi> Matth. 11.28. <hi>o</hi> Exod. 12.26, 27. <hi>p</hi> Reu. 22.17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What elſe is required in them that come to this Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:26409:16"/>
            <p> A. A renewed <hi rend="sup">q</hi> hatred of all ſinne, an heartie endeauour to ouercome naturall paſſions, and an vtter and wel-aduiſed forſaking of <hi rend="sup">r</hi> groſſer ſins, willingnes <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> to be ſtrengthened in faith, and a <hi rend="sup">t</hi> longing deſire for the good of our brethren, <hi>q</hi> Luk 3.12.13. Matth. 18.3. <hi>r</hi> Luke 14.28.29. &amp;c. <hi>ſ</hi> Matth. 5.6. <hi>t</hi> Mark. 11.25. Matth. 5.23.24.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What if a man find himſelfe weake in faith, and full of doubting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Hee muſt bewaile <hi rend="sup">u</hi> his vnbeleefe, pray for faith, ſeeke to haue his doubts reſolued and ſo receiue, to bee further <hi rend="sup">w</hi> ſtrengthened. <hi>u</hi> Marke 9.24. <hi>w</hi> Iudg. 6.36.37. Exod. 12.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ought a mans heart to be affected in receiuing the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. With <hi rend="sup">g</hi> reuerence, ioy and <hi rend="sup">h</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, meditating <hi rend="sup">i</hi> on the outward ſignes, &amp; what they ſignifie, the dainties prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and loue of him that prepared them our communion with Chriſt his graces, &amp; his faithfull people, wherby the heart, is prepared to thankſgiuing. <hi>g</hi> Exod. 3.5. Gen. 28.17. <hi>h</hi> Deut. 16.15. <hi>i</hi> 1. Cor. 11.25 1. King. 8.66.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt we do after we haue receiued?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:26409:17"/>
            <p> A. Wee muſt endeauour to finde an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of <hi rend="sup">k</hi> faith, loue, and all ſauing gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, abounding more and more in weldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>k</hi> Pro. 4.18. Ezek. 47.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What order hath the Lord lefe in his Church, to keepe this ordinances from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The vnruly ſhould be <hi rend="sup">l</hi> admoniſhed, the obſtinate <hi rend="sup">m</hi> excommunicated, and the penitent after their fal reſtored &amp; <hi rend="sup">n</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. <hi>l</hi> 1. Theſ. 5.14. <hi>m</hi> 1. Cor. 5.5. <hi>n</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cor. 2.6, 7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Beſides the forenamed meanes, are there not ſome other profitable for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes: <hi rend="sup">o</hi> reading or hearing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures read, in <hi rend="sup">p</hi> publique, and in <hi rend="sup">q</hi> priuate, <hi rend="sup">r</hi> meditation, and <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> conference. <hi>o</hi> Reu. 1.3 <hi>p</hi> Act. 13.15. <hi>q</hi> Act. 8.30. <hi>r</hi> Luke 2.51. <hi>ſ</hi> Heb. 3.13. Ioh. 4.52.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hitherto of the ordinary meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by faith is increaſed: Be there not alſo ſome extraordinary meanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes: and thoſe bee holy <hi rend="sup">a</hi> faſting, holy <hi rend="sup">b</hi> feaſting, and religious <hi rend="sup">c</hi> vowes. <hi>a</hi> Luke 5.35. <hi>b</hi> Eſter 9.17. <hi>c</hi> Pſal. 50.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is an holy Faſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A religious <hi rend="sup">d</hi> abſtinence from all the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26409:17"/>labours <hi rend="sup">e</hi> of our calling, and <hi rend="sup">f</hi> comforts of this life, ſo farre as comelines and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie will permit, that we might bee more ſeriouſly <hi rend="sup">g</hi> humbled before God, and more feruent in prayer. <hi>d</hi> Eſter. 4.16. <hi>e</hi> Leuit. 23.28. <hi>f</hi> Exod. 35.5. <hi>g</hi> Dan. 9.9.11. Leui. 23.27</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When ought we to fast?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. When we feele or <hi rend="sup">h</hi> feare ſome grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous calamitie vpon vs, or hanging ouer our heads, want ſome ſpeciall bleſſing, are preſſed with ſome ſpeciall ſinne, or goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome <hi rend="sup">i</hi> weighty matter. <hi>h</hi> Eſter 4.16. Ezra 8.21. <hi>i</hi> Acts 13.2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is an holy Feast?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. An extraordinary <hi rend="sup">k</hi> thankſgiuing for ſome notable deliuerance out of ſome deſperate danger, teſtified with feaſting before God, with ioy and gladneſſe, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding preſents to our friends, &amp; <hi rend="sup">l</hi> portions to the needy. <hi>k</hi> 1. Chron. 16.8. &amp; 29, 10, 11 <hi>l</hi> Neh. 8.10. Heſt. 9.22.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is a Religious vow?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A ſolemne <hi rend="sup">m</hi> promiſe vnto God, made by a fit perſon, of ſome lawfull thing which is in his choiſe, to teſtifie his loue <hi rend="sup">n</hi> and thankfulneſſe. <hi>m</hi> Deut. 23.21.22. <hi>n</hi> Pſal. 116.12.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:26409:18"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>Can faith being wrought and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in vs, be fruitleſſe and vnprofitable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: for it worketh <hi rend="sup">o</hi> by loue, <hi>o</hi> Gal. 5.6.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the principall worke of faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It purifieth the heart. Acts 15.9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat followeth thereupon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A fighting and combating againſt ſinne and corruption. Gal. 5.17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Renouncing <hi rend="sup">p</hi> of all euill in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of groſſe <hi rend="sup">q</hi> ſinne in life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. <hi>p</hi> Acts 38. <hi>q</hi> Acts 19.18, 19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is a third thing that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Loue <hi rend="sup">r</hi> and delight in that which is good, ioyned with a ſincere deſire, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, &amp; end euour <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> daily to amend what ſoeuer is amiſſe, and to lead a life <hi rend="sup">t</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the law of God. <hi>r</hi> Pſal. 119.97. <hi>ſ</hi> Phil. 3.13, 14. Acts 11.23. <hi>t</hi> Pſal. 119.6</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein is the ſumme of the law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. In the tenne Commaundements, Deut. 10.4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How are they diuided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Into two Tables, Deut. 5.22. and 10.1, 2.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:26409:18"/>
            <p> Q <hi>Which are the Commandements of the first Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A The foure firſt, &amp; they teech the duty which we owe vnto God immediately.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which are the Commandements of the ſecond Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The ſixe laſt, which inſtruct vs in our dutie towards our neighbour.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Which is the firſt Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I am the Lord thy God, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt haue, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Which is the generall dutie required in this Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That in mind will, affections, and the effects of theſe, wee take the true God, in Chriſt, to be our God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall ſin here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All falling to giue God that foreſaid honour which is due vnto him: or elſe in whole or in part giuing it to any other.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the ſecond Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the generall dutie which this Commandement requireth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That we doe worſhip the true God purely, according to his will.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall ſinne forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All omiſſion of Gods true worſhip
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26409:19"/>when it is required, and al falſe worſhip, either inuented by others, or taken vp of our owne heads.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not take the name, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall dutie required in this Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That we ſhould vſe the titles, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, works &amp; ordinance of the Lord, with knowledge, faith, reuerence, ioy, &amp; ſincerity, in thought, word, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall ſinne forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Omitting the dutie here required, vſing the Lords name when we ought not, or otherwiſe then we ſhould.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When is the name of God taken o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then it ſhould?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. When it is vſed ignorantly, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly without faith, raſhly, not to a right end, hypocritically, falſly, againſt conſcience, and when men name them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Chriſtians, but liue ſcandalouſly.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Remember the Sabbath day, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the general dutie here required</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That the whole Sabbath or Lords day, be ſet apart from al common vſes, as holy to the Lord, both publikely &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26409:19"/>in the practiſe of the duties of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie, holineſſe, and mercie.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the general ſin here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All neglecting of the duties of that time, or prophaning of that day, by need leſſe workes, words, or thoughts, about our callings, or recreation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which day is to be ſet apart as holy to the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is morrall, and perpetuall to keepe one day in ſeuen, as holy: from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the reſurrection of Chriſt, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day was inſtituted, after Chriſt his reſurrection, the firſt day of the weeke was ordained, and is to be kept for euer.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the fift Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Honour thy father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who are to bee vnderstood by father and mother?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Not onely naturall parents, but alſo all ſuperiours in office, age, and gifts.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is it to honour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To acknowledge the excellencie that is in men by vertue of their place, and to carrie our ſelues accordingly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are only the duties of Inferiors here intended.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:26409:20"/>
            <p> A. No, but of Superiors, &amp; equals alſo</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What then is the maine dutie of this Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That we carefully obſerue that order which God hath apointed amongſt men and doe the duties which wee owe vnto them in reſpect of their places &amp; degrees.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the dutie of Inferiors?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They muſt be ſubiect, reuerent, and thankful to their ſuperiors, bearing with their wants, and couering them in loue.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the dutie of Superiours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To carrie themſelues grauely, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and after a ſeemely manner towards their inferiours.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the dutie of equals?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To regard the dignitie and worth each of other, modeſtly to beare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues one toward the other, and in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing honour to goe one before another.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhich is the ſixt Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt doe no Murther.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What is the generall dutie of this Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That by all meanes lawfull, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and ſtudie to preſerue our owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the perſon of our neighbour.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the general ſin herein forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:26409:20"/>
            <p> A. All neglect of our owne, or our nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours preſeruation, or deſire of our own or their hurt, conceiued in heart, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in word, geſture or deed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſeuenth commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not commit Adulterie.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall dutie of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That wee ſhould keepe our ſelues pure in ſoule and body, both towards our ſelues and others.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the generall ſin here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All vncleaneneſſe of heart, ſpeech, geſture, or action, together with all the cauſes, occaſions, and ſignes thereof.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the eight commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not Steale.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the generall duty of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That by all good meanes wee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the outward eſtate of ourſelues, and of our neighbours.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>VVhat is the general ſinne forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All neglect to further our owne or our neighbours wealth, all impeachment or hinderance thereof, and all increaſe thereof, by vniuſt and indirect dealing.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ninth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:26409:21"/>
            <p> A. Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall duty here required</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That by al meanes we ſeek to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our owne and our neighbors good name, according to truth &amp; a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall ſinne forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All failing to procure, defend, and further our own, and our neighbours cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, all vniuſt defence, wrongfull ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and accuſation of our ſelues, or others.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the tenth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not couet, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall duty commanded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That we be truely contented with our owne outward condition, and hartily deſire the good of our neighbour, in all things belonging vnto him great &amp; ſmal</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the generall ſinne forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All thoughts of mind, wiſhes, and deſires of heart, and delightfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances of euill, againſt contentedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is any man able to keepe this Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Not perfectly; for the <hi rend="sup">a</hi> godly often fall, the moſt holy <hi rend="sup">b</hi> faile alwaies in their beſt duties: But the child of God ought, <hi rend="sup">c</hi> may &amp; vſually <hi rend="sup">d</hi> doth walke according
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26409:21"/>to the law, ſincerely. <hi>a</hi> Iam. 3.2. <hi>b</hi> Exod. 28.36, 37, 38. <hi>c</hi> 1. Ioh. 2.14. Ioh. 14.15.21. <hi>d</hi> 1. King. 15.5.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Should not a Christian omit doing of good altogether, ſeeing he cannot doe it in that meaſure that God requireth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: but with diligence, &amp; <hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, ſtriue againſt corruption, looke for <hi rend="sup">f</hi> the aſsiſtance of Gods ſpirit, &amp; labour to <hi rend="sup">g</hi> grow in grace. <hi>e</hi> 2. Cor. 7.1. <hi>f</hi> 2. Chron. 16.9. Phil. 4.13. <hi>g</hi> 1. Pet. 2.2. and 2. Pet. 3.18.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What meanes ſhould a man vſe to grow in grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Hee muſt throughly <hi rend="sup">h</hi> examine his wayes, iudge <hi rend="sup">i</hi> himſelfe, watch <hi rend="sup">k</hi> ouer his heart at all times, in all places, occaſions, and conditions, redeeming the <hi rend="sup">l</hi> time, to ſtore his hart with good, &amp; preſerue <hi rend="sup">m</hi> his faith. <hi>h</hi> Hag. 1.5.7 <hi>i</hi> 1. Cor. 11.31. <hi>k</hi> 2. Tim 4.5. <hi>l</hi> Eph. 5.16. <hi>m</hi> Heb. 10.35, 36, 38.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He muſt take vnto <hi rend="sup">n</hi> him the whole armour of God, and with care, vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and conſtancie, vſe the meanes of <hi rend="sup">o</hi> grace before preſcribed, in on eſtate, <hi rend="sup">p</hi> as well as in another. <hi>n</hi> Eph. 6.14. <hi>o</hi> Prou. 2.3, 4. Col. 4.2. <hi>p</hi> Iob. 27.10.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:26409:22"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>What priuiledges doth God afford in this life vnto his children, who labor accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will to increaſe in grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They may be aſſured <hi rend="sup">q</hi> of his fauour &amp; fatherly <hi rend="sup">r</hi> care ouer them, the <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſpirit, their <hi rend="sup">t</hi> groweth in grace, &amp; <hi rend="sup">u</hi> perſeuerance to the end, <hi>q</hi> 1. Ioh. 3.1 13. Ioh. 1.12. <hi>r</hi> 1. Tim. 4.10. Mat. 10.30. <hi>ſ</hi> Pſal. 143.10. <hi>t</hi> Col. 1.9.10. <hi>u</hi> Phil. 1.6.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>VVhat other priutledges doth God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford vnto them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They are <hi rend="sup">u</hi> kept from, comforted <hi>w</hi> in and deliuered <hi rend="sup">x</hi> out of many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, taught to vſe <hi rend="sup">y</hi> all eſtates aright, <hi rend="sup">z</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from foule offences, enabled to <hi rend="sup">z</hi> riſe againe if they fal, inſtructed to liue <hi rend="sup">a</hi> godly, &amp; haue poſſeſsion <hi rend="sup">b</hi> of the word, <hi>u</hi> Pſal. 32.10. <hi>w</hi> Acts 16.25. <hi>x</hi> Prou. 11.8. <hi>y</hi> Lam. 3.27. Phil. 4.12. 2 Luk. 1.6. <hi>z</hi> Pſal. 37.23, 24. <hi>a</hi> Eph. 2.10. <hi>b</hi> Luke 8.15.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doe all the godly, or any, at all times enioy all theſe priutledges?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: ſome are ignorant of them, not beleeuing, or at leaſt very faintly, that there be any ſuch: Others are careleſſe, who prize, them not, and ſo take not paines for theſe things as they ought.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat other hinderances doe depriue
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26409:22"/>Chriſtans of the enioying of theſe priuiledges</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Inordinate <hi rend="sup">c</hi> paſsions, as feare, anger, ſelfe-loue, pride, loue of pleaſures, cares of the world, earthly incumbrances, and inconſtancie in good duties: temptations alſo to diſtruſt, doe keepe vnder many. <hi>c</hi> Iam. 4.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſhould a man bridle and reforme theſe vnruly paſſions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Let him highly eſteeme a Chriſtian life, pray earneſtly, ſet himſelfe moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the infirmities that be ſtrongeſt in him, ſhun the occaſions of ſinne, hide the <hi>m</hi> commandment in his hart, and <hi rend="sup">n</hi> apply the death of Chriſt, for the killing of corruption. <hi>m</hi> Pſal. 119.11. <hi>n</hi> 1. Ioh. 5.4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may a man ouercome his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to diſtrust?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He muſt not giue credit <hi rend="sup">o</hi> to Satans ſuggeſtions againſt Gods truth but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of Gods <hi rend="sup">p</hi> power, <hi rend="sup">q</hi> goodneſſe, <hi rend="sup">r</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeableneſſe, ormer <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> mercies, &amp; free <hi rend="sup">t</hi> grace in giuing vs his Son: ſo that weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vnworthineſſe, want of feeling com fort ſhould not diſmay him. <hi>o</hi> Mat. 4.3, 4 <hi>p</hi> Mat. 8.2. Eſa. 40.27, 28. <hi>q</hi> Pſal. 51.1. <hi>r</hi> Iere. 31.3 <hi>ſ</hi> Pſal. 77.11.12. <hi>t</hi> Rom. 5.8, 9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What elſe muſt we doe?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:26409:23"/>
            <p> A. Hee muſt conſider what promiſes the Lord hath made to keepe <hi rend="sup">n</hi> &amp; vphold him, what encouragement <hi>w</hi> he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him to beleeue, and how acceptable <hi rend="sup">x</hi> a thing it is that he ſhould ſo do. <hi>u</hi> Mat. 16.18. Luk. 23.32. <hi>w</hi> 1. Ioh. 3.23. <hi>x</hi> Mat. 8.10. &amp; 15.28. Rom. 4.20.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What other thing is to bee learned for the ouercomming of theſe temptations?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Wee muſt iudge of our ſelues not by our owne <hi rend="sup">a</hi> preſent feeling, or by our owne <hi rend="sup">b</hi> diſcerning the fruites of Grace, but by that we haue <hi rend="sup">c</hi> felt, &amp; the <hi rend="sup">d</hi> fruits of grace which appeare to others. <hi>a</hi> Pſal. 116.11. Pſal. 13.1. <hi>b</hi> Pſal. 51.10. <hi>c</hi> Pſal. 77.11. <hi>d</hi> 2. Cor. 2.10, 11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat may be a further helpe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is good to <hi rend="sup">e</hi> examine our hearts, &amp; vſe the aduice of <hi rend="sup">f</hi> others; but we muſt know withall, the groaning <hi rend="sup">g</hi> after, and labouring to reſt our wearied ſoule vpon the promiſes of grace, being neuer ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vntil our doubtfulneſſe be remooued, will bring a good end. <hi>e</hi> Pſa. 4.4. <hi>f</hi> 1. Theſ. 5.14. <hi>g</hi> Mat. 11.28.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doe the fruites of the ſpirit alwayes appeare in the faithfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: they are obſcured in <hi rend="sup">h</hi> our firſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26409:23"/>conuerſion, in the dayes of <hi rend="sup">i</hi> ſecuritie, when we <hi rend="sup">k</hi> leaue our firſt loue, in the time of <hi rend="sup">l</hi> temptation, or of ſome relapſe <hi rend="sup">m</hi> into ſinne. <hi>h</hi> Luke 5.37, 38. <hi>i</hi> 1. Cor. 3. <hi>k</hi> Reue. 2.4. <hi>l</hi> Pſal. 6.1, 2, 3. <hi>m</hi> Pſal. 51.10.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſhould a man recouer out of a relapſe</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By a ſpeedy <hi rend="sup">n</hi> conſideration of what hee hath done, renewing his repentance, with ſorrow and ſhame, <hi rend="sup">o</hi> bewailing his ſinne before God, reforming his life, and laying hold vpon the promiſe of mercy. <hi>n</hi> Reue. 2.5. <hi>o</hi> Iere. 31.18, 19.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>VVhat priuiledges doe the godly enioy as ſoone as this life is ended?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Their glory then begins: for their bodies remaine <hi rend="sup">p</hi> in the graue as in a bed of ſpices, &amp; their ſoules <hi rend="sup">q</hi> being perfectly freed from ſinne, are receiued into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, beholding <hi rend="sup">r</hi> God and Chriſt immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately. <hi>p</hi> 1. Theſ. 4.15. <hi>q</hi> Reuel. 14.13. <hi>r</hi> Mat. 5.8.1. Cor. 13.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If this bee the ſtate of the godly, what ſhall become of the vngodly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Their bodies <hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> ſhall rot in the graue, &amp; their ſoules <hi rend="sup">t</hi> bee iudged to euerlaſting woe. <hi>ſ</hi> Gene. 3.19. <hi>t</hi> Luke 16.22, 23.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When ſhall the happineſſe of the elect be conſummate?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:26409:24"/>
            <p> A. At the <hi rend="sup">u</hi> dreadfull day of iudgment, &amp; the generall reſurrection, <hi>u</hi> Pſal. 17.15</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVho ſhall be the iudge at that day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Chriſt the <hi>w</hi> Lord and King of the Church, whoſhal come in a moſt glorious &amp; viſible maner deſcending <hi rend="sup">x</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen with a ſhout, and with the voice of the Archangel, and with the trumpet of God moſt royally attended with innumerable multitudes of mighty angels. <hi>w</hi> Acts 10.42. &amp; 17.31. <hi>x</hi> 1. The 4.16. <hi>y</hi> 2. The. 1.7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When ſhall he come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He will moſt ſurely come, but the time is <hi rend="sup">z</hi> vnknowne, that we might euer <hi rend="sup">a</hi> watch, and prepare for his comming. <hi>z</hi> Match. 24.36. <hi>a</hi> Matth. 24.42.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whom ſhall he iudge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. His elect and <hi rend="sup">b</hi> choſen, and all their enemies both euill <hi rend="sup">c</hi> angels, and wicked men. <hi>b</hi> 2. Cor. 5.10. <hi>c</hi> 2. Pet. 3.4. Iude v. 16</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Seeing many of Gods elect people, and wicked men are rotted in the earth, how can they be iudged?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The very ſame bodies in <hi rend="sup">d</hi> ſubſtance that at any time died, ſhall by the power of God be raiſed vp, and the ſoules be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited vnto them, inſeparably to abide to gether for euermore. <hi>d</hi> 1. Cor. 15.42, 43.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:26409:24"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>VVhat are wee to beleene concerning thoſe who ſhal be found aliue at the comming of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They ſhall bee changed in the <hi rend="sup">a</hi> twinckling of an eye, and ſo preſented before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt. <hi>e</hi> 1. Cor. 15.51, 52.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what manner ſhall he iudge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Moſt ſtrictly, both in reſpect of the <hi rend="sup">f</hi> perſons iudged, &amp; the things for which; but yet hee ſhall iudge moſt righteous <hi rend="sup">g</hi> iudgement. <hi>f</hi> 2. Cor. 5.10. <hi>g</hi> Acts 17.31.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat ſhall be the iſſue of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the wicked?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Euerlaſting <hi rend="sup">h</hi> perdition from the preſence of the Lord, to all thoſe who ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly or wilfully, did contemn the Goſpell <hi>h</hi> 2. Theſ. 1.7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſhall bee the iſſue thereof to the godly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The cleare viſion of God &amp; Chriſt, endleſſe communion <hi rend="sup">k</hi> with them, and euerlaſting <hi rend="sup">l</hi> peace &amp; glory both in ſoule and body, in fuller meaſure then the heart of man can now comprehend, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Saints enioyed before. <hi>i</hi> 1. Ioh. 3.2. <hi>k</hi> Ioh. 17.24. Phi. 1.23. <hi>l</hi> Mat. 25.34</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
